Guide to the Arthur Ellis collection, 1940-2005 COR0012.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Arthur J. Ellis collection
circa 1940s-2005
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Ellis, Arthur J.
COR0012.MS
4 Linear Feet
Arthur Ellis, notable Washington-based photographer and photojournalist, was born in Washington in 1912 and died in 1989. Ellis joined the Washington Post with the photography staff in 1930. From 1930 to the early 1970s, Ellis captured and shared the life and news of Washington, D.C. Ellis was The Washington Post's photo editor in the early 1950s and chief photographer at the time of his retirement in 1977. Arthur Ellis photographs were exhibited by the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 2003 in the exhibition "Front Page: The Photographs of Arthur Ellis." This collection contains newspaper articles and images and date from the early 1940s through 2005.
Biographical note
Arthur Ellis, notable Washington-based photographer and photojournalist, was born in Washington in 1912 and died in 1989. Ellis began his career at The Washington Post in 1929 as a copy boy and joined the photography staff in 1930. From 1930 to the early 1970s, Ellis captured and shared the life and news of Washington, D.C. Ellis was The Washington Post's photo editor in the early 1950s and chief photographer at the time of his retirement in 1977. During World War II, Ellis volunteered to serve as a motion picture photographer in the US Army.
Arthur Ellis photographs were exhibited by the Corcoran Gallery of Art in 2003 in the exhibition "Front Page: The Photographs of Arthur Ellis." In 2001 Frederica Ellis, Arthur Ellis' widow, bequeathed an endowment to the Corcoran College of Art + Design and established The Arthur J. Ellis Scholarship Fund to provide scholarships for rising first year students in the College's Bachelor of Fine Arts Degree Program in Photojournalism.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Corcoran Institution Board of Trustees donated these records to The George Washington University in 2016. The National Gallery of Art transferred these records to The George Washington University in 2016 following the decision of the Corcoran Institution Board.
Custodial History
The materials of the Arthur Ellis collection were originally donated to the Corcoran Gallery of Art by the estate of Arthur Ellis and his widow Frederica Ellis, along with a collection of photographs.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains newspaper articles and images related to the work of Arthur J. Ellis. The material dates from the 1940s through 2005.
Arrangement
Arranged in no particular order.
- Arthur Ellis press passes, circa 1950-1980 (Box 1)
- Photos: Jurying Corcoran Biennial, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Newsclippings: Corcoran (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photos: Portuguese fisherman taken by Arthur Ellis on vacation with is wife, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photos: Black and white tree taken by Arthur Ellis, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Arthur Ellis Honorable Discharge, 1946 February 7 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Arthur Ellis photography prize from The Washington Newspaper Guild, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Arthur Ellis Certificate of Award from National Photography Contest, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Arthur Ellis certificate for crossing the Artic Circle, 1958 July (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Arthur Ellis plaque commemorating 47 years of service with The Washington Post (Box 2, Item 9)
- Newsclippings: Arthur Ellis photographs published with articles, Cor0003.0.ms (Box 3, Folders 1-8)
- Arthur Ellis portrait with signatures, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Newspapers - Surgery Deaths, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Around DC Newspapers - Weather, Landscapes, Architecture, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Newspapers - Animals, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Newspapers - Around DC News Coverage, Accidents, Fires, Injuries, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Newspapers - Alaska, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Newspapers - Famous People, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Misc. Newspapers, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Everyday Life Newspapers, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Newspapers - Washington Post Ellis, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Political Figures Newspapers - Presidents, Undated; Cor0003.0.ms (Box 6, Folder 2)